Almost every company has now [music]
bought the exact same AI technology as
everybody else. Almost none of them are
getting [music] the results back that
they expected. I spent 30 years inside
the rooms where the world's biggest
companies [music] decide how work
actually gets done. And every single
month I hear from 100 Fortune 500 tech
executives about what's really happening
behind all of the broad announcements.
So today I'm sitting down with Peter
Diamandis to discuss [music] why
companies aren't getting the most out of
AI. Peter founded X-Prize. He co-founded
Singularity University [music] and he
spent his entire career seeing where
technology goes years before the rest of
us even get there. By the end of this
conversation, you're going to know what
[music] the handful of companies who
really are getting great results what
they're doing differently and whether
you can fix the company that you already
have or you need to build a new one. So
Keith, we're we're here in my Moonshot
podcast studio and every week twice a
week, we talk about how fast the AI
world is changing. I mean, I used to be
able to track, you know, entire year of
progress. It's hard to track three days
of progress right now. And I have to
imagine that a lot of companies are both
excited about these tools that are
coming their way, but also fearful about
getting left behind. Uh, how do I best
do this? You know, we're not an AI
native company. How do we compete
against AI native startups? Yeah.
>> What are you seeing inside of companies?
>> You know, this is where I love our
partnership because you're looking at
the technology and you're looking at the
speed and the velocity, the advancements
of technology. I spend every day of my
life in large enterprises working with
the executive teams trying to take that
technology and figure out what to do
with it. And I promise you it is not
nearly at the speed that you're seeing.
>> Yeah. I mean, there are a few companies
out there particularly, you know, the
core tech companies like Anthropic, like
Google, etc. But I even see under the
hoods of those organizations, they're
not even using it with the velocity with
which the technology itself is
advancing. Let's talk for a second about
what's really happening. As you know,
I've got a group of 90 of the Fortune
500s, the chief technology officers, the
chief operating officers, heads of HR,
chief financial officers, and I bring
this group together. And my mission is
very simple. We will help each other
leap forward years by sharing our real
life best practices. No
fireside chats about what's possible.
Everybody comes and they talk about
here's what I'm using AI for. Here's the
results that I've gotten and here's what
you can do. My research institute has to
scrape to find these examples.
>> So is it that they are not actually
getting the kinds of breakthroughs that
they imagine they're going to get or are
they not experimenting enough? Because I
mean the problem with large corporations
is they're so stuck in their ways and
everybody's you know protecting their
fifdom. Are they running the
experiments? I I've created a model that
I help my teams understand that there's
three ways of thinking about AI
implementation inside of a company. One
is the the fundamental redesign of your
company, right? So, Amazon fundamentally
redesigned the future of publishing,
commerce, etc. They they saw technology
back in at the time and they reinvented
an entire industry. There's that
possibility. The next possibility is how
do you take what you do every day? I'm a
procurement person and I'm buying
>> Yeah. How do I use AI to re-engineer the
workflows of what I do every single day?
That's not the third area, which is how
do I use the tools to improve
productivity? The problem is that most
companies, they first access to AI
relative to the the tools. So all of a
sudden you got Claude or Chat GBT
available to you or Gemini available to
you. It wouldn't be a surprise that a
single individual thinking about how to
use a tool differently wouldn't find
radical results, right? They're going to
see productivity enhancements. and and I
do see that depending upon the space
engineering 50 to 80% improvement in
productivity of specific engineers not
everybody can use the tools well so we
should talk about how do you get your
people using the tools better to advance
productivity of their particular role
now the second place as you well know AI
is not new it's been around for a long
time so how do you think about how AI
re-engineers the product of your company
the technology companies have been using
AI for a long time that's been around
and the question is how do we rethink
business models entirely new business
models to rethink the company and that's
number two and then the place where
we're gaining the least traction but
it's the greatest possibility is
re-engineering workflows and I can say
that customer service is the place that
will make the greatest impact today
we're going to be seeing the absolute
elimination of call centers down to the
very basics we're going to be seeing
significantly improved customer
experience so that is actually gone
further than anyone else and we can talk
about the successes there sales support
is another one freeing sales people up
to sell and that's been a big and what I
zerobased workflow redesign. And then
the um the third area is going to be
supply chain. Those are the areas where
we're going to see the biggest impact.
And those are the ones that we've been
able to find the real research. YC is a
is the largest incubator in the world,
right? 200 companies a quarter that give
them each a half a million bucks. So
hund00 million a quarter. Yeah.
>> And they're birthing these companies. I
think 12% of all unicorns come out of
YC. These kids think differently.
>> Yeah. They're AI they're AI natives.
fully.
>> I mean I mean these companies are built
from the ground up using AI at every
process.
>> Exactly. And I was talking to these kids
getting to know them talking to Gary Tan
who runs this thing and Gary had created
this superbrain to run the company to
run YC. So everything that everybody
does at YC was entered into AI and all
of the workflows were in AI. You queried
the business out of that and the AI was
actually constantly refining the
workflows. So, you know, it's like there
was never a need to set an agenda for a
meeting. AI would do that. The
accountability of did we do something
was always being prompted by AI. The
workflow improvement. There's a company
called Red Hat, which you might know.
>> I remember Red Hat. Sure.
>> And it's it was a was bought by IBM.
>> Yeah.
>> Matt Hicks had an idea separately from
what he saw there of creating a superb
brain for a 20,000 person company. So,
what he did is he had all of the people
at the executive team level write a
10-page dossier of okay, you're the
finance head, you're the HR head. I want
you to write a 10-page dossier is all of
the workflows that you do.
>> What do you do every day?
>> What do you do every day? What are the
things that the com your group does?
Then he had the same 10 page of
everybody who reports to each of them,
right? So now you've got two layers of
deep documentation from your brain, what
you do and how you do it and you put
that into the AI. Then they went over to
Service Now and they took which is a
process re-engineer. They took all of
the inputs from Service Now and they put
that into the AI. Then they put a plugin
to the ERM system which allowed all the
data to flow about what's going on here.
So now Matt Hicks has the opportunity to
sit there and say, "Wait a second. I see
that New England uh sales isn't as good
as um Florida sales. I want to know what
are they doing different,
>> right? Fundamental insights you'd never
have before.
>> An executive would have had to ask that
question and and maybe got an answer two
weeks later." And in the meantime,
somebody would have been covering up
what like it would have been
And even even better, the New England
office can actually query the AI. How
can I get as good as the uh you know the
team down in in Orlando
>> and more importantly underneath it all
the AI is making recommendations of the
re-engineering of the workflow. So I was
working with Cisco uh in a research
project and we were looking at how what
are the best practices of some person in
procurement to re-engineer the endto-end
workflows of supply chain because we all
know that a person in procurement needs
sales forecasting it needs manufacturing
scheduling. there's all when end to end
is the issue right so we're trying to
get this and we're coming up with the
best methodology for zerobased workflow
redesign and then when I saw what Matt
was doing I was like wow we don't even
have to do that down here AI partner it
falls out of it right
>> so th this is extraordinary what's about
to happen if this superbrain becomes
commercialized which right now there's
nobody commercializing it I'm now in the
process of working with some folks to do
that if it becomes commercialized the
corporate advancement of the use of AI
to fundamentally re-engineer the way
corporations work, the old change
management won't matter anymore. The
fact that somebody's holding back
information or somebody's scared about
something, etc., it won't matter anymore
and that will be a major unlock, massive
unlock.
>> Agreed. So, you know, this is what
Elon's vision for macroard as well,
right? Which is digitizing all your
employees and it takes it a step
further. Uh, and there are other
companies doing this. Rather than you
writing down what you do, the AI is
observing you during the day all week
and it's documenting exactly what you
do. Yeah,
>> at a level of fidelity. I mean,
>> that easier in an engineering based
company. Sure. Than a company where
you're not necessarily plugged into
observability as you
>> or you're recording every phone call,
every Zoom and you're allowing
>> ambient listening.
>> Yes.
>> Across corporations, I'm surprised how
quickly that picked up.
>> Yeah, for sure.
>> Even major companies like
>> the implications of this are immense. I
mean, it's about increasing corporate
efficiency, right?
>> Talk about fear.
>> Yeah. And it's the good news is the
companies are going to become much more
productive, much more efficient. The
cost will come down. And what we've seen
as well, of course, in one of the
conversations you and I have talked
about, I think at the end of the day, a
company that's doing X amount of revenue
and work can accomplish that with
ultimately 80% fewer employees
potentially.
>> And that leads to fear. I mean, there
were, you know, everything from Amazon
workers wearing glasses that's recording
what they're doing. teaching the robots
that will eventually replace them. We
saw that at Meta as well. And that's got
to like I'm training my company's AI to
ultimately replace me.
>> Yeah.
>> I want to use an example of a large
governmental institution. Maybe I
shouldn't say who it is yet. I just
won't, but it's it's one we all know.
And uh
>> one of the US government
>> one of the US government departments.
And the leader of it
>> that that you coach
>> that I coach and the leader of it I have
such admiration for and such respect
for. I I told a joke to him and I said,
"Hey, you you know the joke." He was
talking about how does he communicate to
his people in the institution and I
said, "Well, you know the joke. Two
hikers walking along the path and a bear
comes out of the woods and uh one hiker
starts running and the other hiker
pauses and puts on his tennis shoes and
the guy looks back and says, "What the
hell are you doing? You're putting on
your tennis shoes. You can outrun a
bear." And uh the guy looks up and goes,
"Don't worry. I don't have to outrun the
bear. I just have to outrun you."
>> Yeah.
>> And I frankly, you look, you and I are
very competitive.
>> Yeah. And I think that that's by the way
in some organizations that's a valuable
message to say get off your ass.
>> Yes.
>> And put on your tennis shoes and become
a AI relevant or you'll be out of
>> be the 20%.
>> Be the 20%. So like you and I can you
know we get excited about something like
that. And he said no no that's not my
message. He said my message is I am
committed to every single employee in
this agency that I'm going to make them
more competitive than anybody in the
industry even in the private sector. I'm
gonna give every one of them a chance to
step up and be extraordinary. And I was
like, okay, that's a better message,
[laughter]
>> right? But so my so what
>> and so that doesn't exist most anywhere
today. And it needs a caring leader and
it needs a process.
>> I grew up as you know in manufacturing.
My job, my desire and design out of life
was I wanted to change the future of
American manufacturing and this was a
day when the Japanese which was using
six sigma, TQM etc. was trusting
frontline teams, incrementally changing
culture. What I realized, Peter, is
culture is not tough to change.
>> Really
>> not tough to change at all. Just have to
change process
>> and the culture falls out
>> and the culture is the process. So when
the lethargic top- down command and
control organizations of American steel
were beaten quickly by the Japanese who
had small teams iterating every day.
Their process was small teams iterating
better quality improvement, continuous
process improvement. They got higher
quality and lower price points. Process
change. Agile was a process change over
over waterfall. It changed the culture.
Anybody who was ever present at the
transformation of process change. There
was a period of time in in American
manufacturing where safety numbers were
bad. They changed the process of safety
which elevated safety but also elevated
a culture of care of of focus. I
realized that my old brain as an
industrial engineer focused on process
is in fact how we change culture and
that's how we change high performing
team culture through process. You you've
experienced my stress testing and things
like that.
>> Yeah.
>> So what we did in this case is I I just
dusted off the old manual for six sigma
black belts and we're now coming
together and we're creating AI black
belts in companies. So we say to a we
was just down at Lowe's we had the
entire company present and it was AI day
and we were inviting people to be black
belts of AI. If anybody raised their
hand and said, "I want to get better."
They were a yellow belt, right? And so
they they learned all the tools and
learned how to use the tools and they
got put into small peer-to-peer groups
of other yellow belts. And we put
somebody who was highly proficient in AI
in their particular role, knowing how to
do it in their role. We put it in small
peer-to-p peer coaching groups, organic
coaching groups, and it was a black
belt. It was coaching the yellow belt,
>> right? And then as people get more
proficient, and proficiency means
showing results and outcomes from their
use of tools, because this was the other
miss that a lot of companies made. They
just wanted you to burn tokens, which I
I I've heard you and Jensen and people
talk about, of course, Jensen, by the
way, is token maxing. It's his job,
right?
>> But no, no, it's not about token maxing.
It's about how can you show measurable
outcomes. So to get to a brown belt,
you've got to show measurable outcomes
from your yellow belt tool use. And then
once you're at brown belt then the next
stage is can you start to redesign the
workflows around you not just the use of
tools to get to black belt and are you
willing to teach
>> right
>> so we've created we use positive
psychology a sense of ownership and
branding and celebration and winning and
and peer-to-peer you know how much
>> elevation
>> and elevation co-levation it's the
principle of my work around co-ation
>> so that's the process we brought to this
government institution and a number of
others and they're crushing it
>> that process can help a company increase
its efficiency per employee and as you
said it's going to weed out those who
don't jump on the bandwagon,
>> right?
>> Those who are adding value per unit time
or unit token are are going to help the
company grow and a growing company
employs them and more and more others.
But the notion that in fact we're going
to see efficiency of companies and I I
think what hasn't hit yet is the massive
increase in agentic systems that are
coming and and so there is going to be a
downsizing in companies.
>> Now double click on this with me. Give
me an example what you mean by aentic
systems. You mean higher supply chains.
I was with uh I was with Michael Katios
who's the head of office of science and
technology policy yesterday interviewing
for moonshots and we're talking about uh
the idea that uh in the research world
what's likely to happen I mean so how
does research occur today at at
companies and at universities uh there's
an individual who sets up uh you know
thinks through an experiment designs the
experiment runs the experiment but where
we're heading towards is those no longer
individuals those are now agents who uh
are asked to maximize breakthroughs in
particular materials. They design the
experiments. They run the experiments on
robotic systems. They get the data and
they run it again and it's running a
million times faster than humans.
>> Yeah. And
>> with no humans in the loop and and human
only thing that humans are doing are
guiding like we want a better material
to do this.
>> One of the things that woke me up uh was
watching IBM is you know IBM is the
leading large company on
>> in quantum.
>> In quantum.
>> Yeah. So where they've already started
using quantum for big results is in R&D
just everything you're talking about and
then that like stick in a lightning bolt
to its it
>> but one could imagine going from just
beyond research and science to designs
of products like having agents research
what do people need and then come up
with products and then put them up on
the web and have them get the data and
are people buying it and then let's
iterate. You know, when I was
interviewing Eric Schmidt in this room,
he talked about learning loops. That the
most successful companies in the world
are running learning loops. They're
running experiments, getting data,
refining their thesis, and running it.
This will all go towards agents doing
these
>> just like the superbrain. I mean, it's
basically that's the that's the
beginning of it, right? And so, this
obviously brings up the question that
you and I want to maybe segue into. What
is the societal impact here?
>> There is confusion about what the data
is saying. There was a huge amount of
fear. We had uh Dario and Sam Alman and
others talking about you know we're
going to AI is going to replace all of
these jobs and it was a job job
apocalypse and we now have a number of
them reversing position backpedaling and
we see a number of individuals who are
saying listen technology forever has
created more jobs and opportunities than
it's eliminated. It's changed what
people do but ultimately on the whole
there's more opportunity. We've now
swung from job apocalypse to creating a
whole bunch of new jobs. In my mind,
it's more the soloreneur and it's the
smaller companies.
>> So, can I let me get into what I've been
really thinking about and it was
interesting. I had to go back again to
my roots to understand what's happening
here today,
>> please.
>> So, uh I grew up in Pittsburgh. My dad
was an unemployed steel worker. did a
little bit of research and when the rust
belt collapsed, there were about 450,000
jobs lost in about a 10-year period in
the steel industry in the United States.
And um and my dad was one of those,
>> right?
>> At the very same time, everybody always
says, "Well, Pittsburgh has thrived. It
rejuvenated."
>> And it's true. Over a period of time, um
more than more than 5 million jobs were
created,
>> right? Even in in that area alone.
Yet when you fly into Pittsburgh with me
to go visit my mom and we drive out
Route 30 and we go out along Manonga
Hala River, there's shanty towns and
[clears throat] people like if my if my
mom didn't have me, she'd be living on
welfare. Pensions were erased from my
father. They didn't have any.
>> And uh and there's entire populations.
Now, what happened to that group of
individuals? Those people were never
retrained. You're not going to retrain
my father, a 45-year-old steel worker
ditch digger. You got to retrain him to
go to work in a self-driving automotive
car at CMU, right?
>> It's not going to be his thing, right?
That role was displaced.
>> Yes.
>> Now, what happened to that role? They
became disenfranchised with the
Democratic party. They were Democrats.
They were bluecollar Democrats all our
life. That group is maggot today. That
group is now a group of so frustrated
individuals that the the Democrats of
the Clinton era, etc., did not serve
them
>> that they were looking for other
opportunities. Some of them want to blow
up the system right
>> now. What we're about to do without a
question is we're going to at least lose
a couple million jobs that are not going
to get retrained in this new world. A
call center worker who's sitting at a
call center.
>> Yes.
>> And that is going to be moving over to
AI and we're going to be more satisfied
with that interaction than we currently
are with a human who can't access all
the information available to them. um
and give us really cool new things etc.
That job is gone.
>> Yes.
>> So what I started to realize was it's
not a macro question. Stop talking about
the macro. It disguises the problem and
we can't fix it at a macro level. I said
I'm just going to go simple. We're going
to create a nonprofit called Workbridge.
Uh we named this this uh idea and we're
going to go to large corporations that
have call centers. We're going to by the
way we're going to stack all the roles.
>> In other the roles that are most likely
to be displaced first. We know call We
know customer service reps are gone.
>> Yeah,
>> but not gone. They're 20% of 80%.
There's going to be places for them. But
let's stack that role now. Let's fix it
for that role. Let's save 2 million
people. I don't need mean jobs. Let's
save 2 million people. This is an AI
first mindset.
>> So these individuals will no longer be
doing what they've been doing. Now you
can you can take that role and the first
thing you look at is are there are there
things that you can notice in your
customer experience that actually could
be done by a human today that aren't
just answering a phone call.
>> IKEA [clears throat] do you know the
IKEA right? So you know the example of
what they did
>> please
>> 85,000 employees were about to be lost
from their call centers and they
realized that they had they saw data
that showed there was a der of people in
their system that could help you
redesign your house with IKEA products
and that's a much more intimate thing
and AI wasn't going to do that and so
they were able to to replace any the the
you know sarcastic person me says is he
going to do that yet?
>> Yes. No. No. Exactly. But but I'm okay
with that. We're workbridge. The idea is
we go to a company um like a large
financial services institution and say,
"Look, you've got you've got 20,000
people in your call centers and you know
right now you want to get rid of 2,000
of them, but you're afraid that if you
get rid of 2,000, it's going to create
fear and low customer satisfaction among
the the 18,000."
>> Very true.
>> Right.
>> Right. The next So, you're kind of
holding on to them and you're waiting
until you can get rid of 50% of them at
once and say it's done for now. Right.
said, ' Let's not do that. Let's create
a beautiful package [clears throat]
that allows somebody to say, listen, 50%
of you will be gone, but we've got the
coolest place for you to go.
>> Mhm.
>> And there's three options. One is
there's an internal set of like
companies like Elevance and other um
healthcare companies. We could very
quickly, even inside their own system,
move somebody from currently being a
call center person to elder care or
something in in in human care, in
nursing, etc. So, there's internal skill
transfer. Then there's external jobs
that do require new training and
development. We can give people an
entire work bridge into a new place. And
yes, there is going to be a third path
that you and I have talked about a lot,
which is the universal basic income and
those kind of things. And you know, and
we're even designing that because that
one we are going to have to work with
government. But I do believe that we
could create a marketplace where an
individual could um could go on to a
task rabbit like system and shop for
cool things that they could be doing
that would advance society. And in order
to get their monthly income, they've got
to earn points from being generous in
local society and they can badge it and
we can make people feel good about it.
So the bottom line is we're going to
create a package called workbridge and
I'm working with the um former governor
of of uh Virginia um Glenn Ynan who's
just an extraordinary guy was the CEO of
uh Carlile
>> just a such a clean thinker and he and I
have been a blast because I'm bringing
the large corpor corporations he's
bringing his knowledge of government and
governors which will be a big partner in
all of this and I'm really excited about
this but we're just starting at one
place. I I don't I don't have time for
these conversations that say we
don't have to worry because 10 million
jobs will be created. right?
>> I don't have time for the catast the
catastrophizing that frankly you and I
were doing for a while because we were
scared. I'm like I'm like, "Okay, get
out of your mind, Keith. Let's just
solve the problem.
>> Put something in place that actually
solves it and demonstrate." I mean, I I
think the most important thing is
creating a demonstration that other
people can model, right? Um Exactly. And
at the end of the day, uh, I think the
government is left holding the bag on on
these individuals. So, you're either
going to be supporting
>> don't do it in the States. Nobody helped
those people like my father. Government
was holding the bag and welfare is not
going to do it.
>> Yeah.
>> Like, we've got to we we we owe them
better than that. And in fact, you know,
you you've heard, you know, you've
talked to me about this. Elon has teased
the idea that potentially he'll give a
big chunk of his money away or what
Michael Dell is doing right now with
with uh uh with Gersner and the team
around the Trump accounts.
>> Yeah,
>> I do think there's an opportunity to go
to the billionaire trillionaire
population and say there's a swath of
population here that's going to be left
out, but I want to give them purposeful
exciting pl things to do. Make them a
functional part of society, not
disenfranchised like my dad's
population. And we'll we'll create
systems around that. So, I'm actually
more more positive, Peter, than I ever
have been because I I think we we're
starting to see that there is a
transitionary roadmap that if we put our
mind to it, and this is what happened
when you and I were talking about the
the you know, what are we going to do?
We have to when the pitchforks come out,
what are we going to do? Yeah. Kind of
conversations. I said to these people
who were saying it was going to happen.
Now, let's start planning. And it was
through forcing people like you know
Steve Jervenson and others saying guys
what would we do now that I started to
come up with this and that's how we
created workbridge.
>> That's great and it needs to be
replicated you know hundreds of times
over.
>> Well we're going to we're going to scale
it.
>> And by the way you know AI is the
greatest teacher of all in in terms of
helping somebody re-educate or retool
themselves
>> from the bottom up. And I think that's
something the tech causing the problems
are also the greatest tools to help us
solve the problems. So, if you like this
content, I hope you'll subscribe.